my name is Kayla Thomas and this is
Diabetes Awareness Month so of course
that's a perfect fitting topic for today
joining me to discuss it is Tracy
Jackson who's a diabetes educator thank
you for being here thank you for having
me you bet and of course before we start
a disclaimer that we always like to
bring you the contents of this chat is
for informational purposes only if you
have any questions specific to your
health or medical condition you want to
direct those towards your doctor however
if you have any questions about diabetes
about an event that we're gonna tell you
about tomorrow go ahead and post those
in comments we're gonna do our best to
monitor those during the live broadcast
and of course if you're watching this
later in the day we'll keep an eye on
those comments and questions and get you
answers as fast as we can provide that
so let's start with some lingo I think
diabetes is a term a lot of people are
familiar with they might have heard
things like pre diabetes type 1 diabetes
type 2 diet and on what diabetes is and
who is most likely to get it okay
diabetes is just basically an elevation
in blood sugars it occurs for different
reasons depending upon what type of
diabetes it is so and some people don't
know what type of diabetes they have
which is kind of the really that's
something they should know right so type
one diabetes is an autoimmune condition
that happens based on maybe they get
sick with some type of virus instead of
attacking the virus their immune system
attacks the part of their pancreas that
produces insulin so people with type 1
diabetes produce no insulin okay which
basically you can't sustain life if you
do not produce insulin you cannot
process your food for fuels so it is
yeah
medical intervention is yes absolutely
and usually those people get very sick
very quickly so they know something
major is happening so type 2 then type 2
is is more of a slow onset a lot of
people will have elevated blood sugars 5
or 10 years before they even know that
they have type 2 diabetes or get
diagnosed with it it's more of condition
of insulin resistance meaning their
body's producing insulin but it's not
working as well as it should an insulin
job is to get the sugar out of your
bloodstream sugar gets into the
bloodstream from the food that we
and that's a necessary response to food
and I know a lot of people who have
diabetes say well why is my body
changing food to sugar
everybody's does it it's just with
diabetes the insulin doesn't work or
they don't have it and that sugar can't
leave the bloodstream or can't enough of
it can't leave the bloodstream so that's
the difference between type 1 and type 2
insulin not using well and type 2 and no
insulin with type 1 what are some of the
risk factors that go in like family
history play a big role absolutely yeah
especially with type 2 diabetes it's
very genetically linked so if somebody
has a mother or a father with type 2
they're they're pretty genetically at
risk but there is a lifestyle factor
attached to as well so you might have
that gene but if people are staying
active and they're keeping an eye on
their weight and they're eating a you
know a nutritious well-rounded diet then
they're not as at high you know at as
high of a risk as if they're maybe not
minding those lifestyle activities I
think sometimes we get kind of lacks we
you know maybe go to the doctor every
once in a while sometimes we don't
always pay attention to the changes in
our body what are some of the first
signs or symptoms that somebody should
maybe look at that there may be
developing pre-diabetes right right
right
I didn't describe pre-diabetes to go me
to say yeah that's a head and jump back
this is like there's nothing so
pre-diabetes is basically blood sugars
that are not low enough to be considered
normal but not high enough to be
considered diagnostic for diabetes so
it's kind of gray area in between when I
mentioned what type to a lot of people
might have elevation in blood Sugar's
five to ten years before being diagnosed
for a lot of people that's at
pre-diabetes zone can you reverse that
well that's that's a question like can
you cure right sure or do you just
manage and can you cure pre-diabetes or
can you just kind of hang out there for
a mile or can you back it down all
that's we know we can prevent it from
becoming type 2 diabetes because there's
a large study going on on that but the
problem is that I always tell people we
don't know if that's a nap
Aleut because you have to take a group
of individuals and study them for their
lifetime
and if they didn't have diabetes at the
time of their death and yes we prevented
it right sure but that's just such a
hard thing to say but we definitely know
we can keep their blood Sugar's down
whether they have pre-diabetes type 2
diabetes type 1 diabetes the goal is to
keep it more normal even if they're
diagnosed with diabetes right so we're
managing it to reduce the risk of
complications okay so that's healthier
for them in the long run mm-hmm
we're wearing our blue today plume is
actually the color of Diabetes Awareness
Month and tomorrow November 14th happens
to be World Diabetes Day we have a
special event going on here at the Maine
Nebraska Medical Center campus which is
where we're located right now of course
have locations all over the city but if
you're interested in finding out more
this diabetes Fair is a great
educational opportunity what's planned
for tomorrow and who should come well
it's it's a World Diabetes Day event
that's kind of a global awareness of
diabetes and its impact on health and
the theme for this year is diabetes and
the family so it's focusing on your risk
of diabetes so if I have a father or
grandfather with diabetes I need to be
aware of my risk for diabetes it's also
focusing on how to be in a family with
people who have diabetes
yes how do I properly support these
individuals and my family that have
diabetes so we're having several
different community partners come we try
to kind of work with in this
neighborhood we have a lot of resources
right here in the area so we're having
like the Omaha Parks and Rec Department
coming because they have a lot of
community centers that have gyms that
people can workout in and programs that
they have fitness kinds of things we're
having some of the diabetes supply
companies come and show their products
for ways to make people's lives easier
with living with diabetes we're gonna
personally have some information on
nutrition and risk factors for diabetes
so it's it should be fun very
interactive and a good opportunity if
people have questions to come in
solutely so anybody who you know wonders
about their risk of diabetes who has a
family member
ladies who works you know even a health
care professional that works with people
who have diabetes that would be perfect
well in a great opportunity if you have
somebody in your household as well for
maybe helping them as much as you can
and then learning for yourself you know
potentially about prevention and
anything you can do particulars on the
event it is 11:30 to 1 o'clock tomorrow
yes located in the Durham outpatient
center which is near 44th and Emily you
can valet park is that a good yes yes
you can valet park or we have the green
parking garage as well there so we have
the information on our Facebook page and
there's a Facebook event so if you're
interested in coming tomorrow and here
fun fact about World Diabetes Day why is
November 14th World Diabetes Day Tracy
always on November 14th because that's
one of the cofounders of insulin the
doctor that co-founded insulin it's his
birthday
so it's always on November 14th
regardless of when that falls and
obviously insulin is about the most
important element when it comes to this
topic that it's absolutely and and from
the time he Co discovered it it
certainly has changed and gotten better
so great opportunities to learn about
nutrition to learn about managing
diabetes and I love the idea of bringing
in the whole family because this isn't
something that you have to face by
yourself and you might not even be aware
of the team that Tracy's a part of here
at Nebraska medicine what does your team
do and how can you help people that have
diabetes we basically manage every level
so we have physicians here who are
specialists in diabetes we have nurse
case managers that help out the
physician in the visit and also follow
up with the patient on anything they
might need at home we have diabetes
educators like myself that can help
control because maybe the patient just
needs a little help with meal planning
maybe they just need a little bit of
adjustments to their insulin do the
thinking for me all right but anymore
like I said we're technology has
advanced sometimes absolutely we're
getting a lot of assistance from that
and that can help with support too you
know when when people have more data to
share with other people so so definitely
we have kind of a multi-level approach
and it's really you know a whole person
constant
where we're helping people in you know
in the office but also over the phone
and when they come back for visits and
we're on the computer they upload
information from devices and we can help
them over the phone to make their life
easier and help with all that
information so the event tomorrow great
opportunity to come learn more I think
November is this time of year that a lot
of us kind of start to like we love and
we dread because it's kind of a
free-for-all like the treats come out
everyone talked Allah covered everything
like I'm already dreaming about mashed
potatoes and gravy and pumpkin pie but
when it comes to thinking about your own
health and nutrition this time of year
or maybe hosting an event where you may
have people who are diabetic what advice
do you have
don't don't think it's anything special
you know I mean people with diabetes can
eat real food like everybody else eats
so it's not like they have to have
special food if there are your typical
things at the dinner those are things
that they can eat they just need to
portion control like basically we all
should be doing right really you tell
people that all the time a diet for
somebody with diabetes is no different
than what everybody else should be
eating the person with diabetes has more
of a immediate reason to pay attention
to that but really everybody should be
doing the same thing just watching
portions eating a balanced diet you know
more nutritious foods versus more empty
calorie foods it's really just basics
that work for them it's just kind of
getting the ideas and we don't need to
eat everything else there's plenty to
spread out I can have us looked over
later one more question for you since
we're kind of talking about the topic of
the fair tomorrow and kind of embracing
the family I think sometimes were the
last ones to notice things in ourselves
if you live with someone and you think
something's not right I think it might
be time what signs are symptoms would
you point out to say that you've got a
loved one this might be a sign that
they're diabetic and it's time to see
some right
right because a lot of the the symptoms
of type 2 diabetes aren't really
lightning-bolt yeah I mean they're like
I said they're happening kind of over a
period of time of years sometimes but
somebody who is excessively fatigued
like wow you just have no energy you
know every night you fall asleep and on
the sofa and so I
lack of energy an extreme amount of
thirst so somebody who says I just drink
and drink all day and I still my mouth
is so dry I can't even talk excessive
urination which a lot of people don't
think much about that if they're
drinking a lot and then blurry vision
that is really kind of the thing that
gets people to stand up and take notice
you know I'm tired that I'm tired for
lots of reasons I'm drinking a lot but
I'm peeing you know those kind of go but
that when people's vision starts to be
affected that is kind of like a little
wake-up call I have a good friend who's
just in her 40s and that was the big
wake-up call too so you know if you know
someone if you love someone if you have
a friend if it's yourself or someone
else good idea to to kind of pay
attention to those signs and heck if
you're thinking about those signs or
symptoms now tomorrow is a great
opportunity to come to meet Tracy and
her team at the World Diabetes Day event
again that's 11:30 to one tomorrow which
is Thursday November 14th at the germ
outpatient center again if you have any
more questions for Tracy or anything you
want to know about the event you can go
ahead and post those in the comment
section anything else you want to add
before we wrap up I don't think so you
did a good job of asking everything I
know and what you don't want more than
that and you'll be telling plenty more
people tomorrow so we hope to see a lot
of you come out tomorrow thanks for
joining us four moments in medicine lie